Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts at the Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- [Full of wickedness], 1857-1859; uva.00267; xxx.00239; xxx.00066; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 15.5 x 8 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The verses on the recto, while not published word-for-word until 1897, seem to represent an early draft of the poem first published as number 13 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in the 1860 Leaves of Grass, and eventually titled You Felons on Trial in Courts. Whitman's careful script and verse forms here also resemble the methods of inscription used for the Live Oak, with Moss poems dated to the post-1856, pre-1860 period. The undeleted notes on the back are titled Poems. A cartoon hand in the left margin points to the phrase "religious emotions." Whitman's use of the title Calamus Leaves dates these notes to the same pre-1860 period as the deleted verses on the recto, since Calamus-Leaves was what he renamed the cluster Live Oak, with Moss before settling on Calamus for the 1860 edition. A section of the notes below the rest (beginning "spirituality—the unknown,...") is inscribed in verse form.
- [From wooded Maine], 1889; uva.00268; xxx.00398; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 11 x 18 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The verso letter is dated "Aug 14th /89," and asks Whitman to send the unidentified writer a copy of the "latest special edition" of Leaves of Grass. These trial verses became part of A Twilight Song—subtitled, "for unknown buried soldiers, North and South"—which was first published in the May, 1890 Century and then included in the second annex Good-Bye My Fancy in the 1892 "deathbed" edition of Leaves.
- [I am become the poet of babes and], about 1855; uva.00269; xxx.00048; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 4 x 14.5 cm pasted to 4.5 x 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The verso lines beginning "I think I could dash the girder of the earth / away" and "Surely I am out of my head!" are deleted with several pencil strokes. The deleted number 209 appears in the top right corner of the lower section. After much revision the recto lines, which are related to lines in Library of Congress Notebook #80, seem to have become part of what would be section 44 of Song of Myself. The verso contains an early draft of lines eventually incorporated in section 27 of the poem.
- [American air I have breathed], about 1855; uva.00270; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 4.5 x 18 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  Although Whitman did not publish these verses himself, their structure and the type of paper upon which they are inscribed suggest a close relationship with the lines on another manuscript in the University of Virginia collection, which were revised to form part of section 14 of Chants Democratic in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass, a set of verses eventually transformed into an independent poem under the title Poets to Come.
- [Merely what I tell is not to justify me], about 1855; uva.00271; xxx.00045; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 4 x 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The lines appearing on the recto of this manuscript bear a strong resemblence to the ideas expressed in the opening lines of section 14 of the poem Chants Democratic appearing in 1860 and which eventually became the independent poem Poets to Come.. The lines on the verso (deleted with several vertical and horizontal pencil strokes) seem to have been rejected.
- [Can ? make me so exuberant yet so faintish], about 1855; uva.00273; xxx.00048; xxx.00271; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6 x 19.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The recto verses bear some similarity to what would eventually form section 28 of Song of Myself, while the deleted lines on the verso (beginning "This mouth is pulled by some sexton for his dismalest fee,") represent a fragment of draft lines eventually incorporated in the sixth poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass, a poem permanently retitled Faces in the 1872 edition.
- [To this continent comes the], 1856-1860; uva.00275; xxx.00047; xxx.00309; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 10 x 13 cm pasted to 5 x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  These lines share common ideas expressed throughout Leaves of Grass, especially in many of the new poems to the 1860 edition. The strongest verbal echoes appear in the poem So long! which expresses very similar ideas and the common words "menacing" and "offspring." The printed words "Leaves of" appearing on the verso indicate that Whitman composed this draft on a piece of paper cover from the 1855 edition.
- [Ships sail upon the waters], 1856-1860; uva.00276; xxx.00180; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 15.5 x 14.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  Part of the word "Leaves" appears in the lower right corner of the verso. On the verso, in blue pencil, appears a note, reading "Drum Taps—City of Ships" which appears to be in Whitman's hand. This may indeed have been a draft of the poem City of Ships, which first appeared in 1865 as part of the independent publication Drum-Taps, but the similarities to the lines on another manuscript in the University of Virginia collection and lack of references to the Civil War indicate that it was inscribed prior to the publication of the the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass.
- [You are English], 1856-1860; uva.00277; xxx.00021; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 10 x 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  Whitman's use of the word "Libertad" and his way of handling the theme of immigration suggest that this might be part of an early draft of the poem eventually known as A Broadway Pageant, first published in the June 27, 1860 issue of the New York Times as The Errand-Bearers.
- [Remember if you are dying], 1855-1859; uva.00278; xxx.00048; xxx.00015; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 8 x 15.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The verso lines (beginning "[sl]ueing,/...[be]nding,/...halt in the shade,") represent a fragment of a polished pre- 1855 -publication draft of lines that would eventually belong in section 13 of Song of Myself. Whitman used this leaf at some point after 1855 to jot down the recto verses perpendicular to the ruled lines. These seem to constitute a complete but very early draft of the poem To One Shortly To Die, first published in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass in the cluster Messenger Leaves. In the upper right corner of the recto appear the words "note / last page of 'Ghost-seers'" in Whitman's hand, suggesting that he had considered forming a cluster under this title, never published, in Leaves of Grass, perhaps in the 1860 edition. The phrase "Ghost-seers" recalls a statement regarding Emerson in Leaves-Droppings, a section of correspondence and commentary Whitman appended to the 1856 edition: "[Emerson] sees the future of truths as our Spirit-seers discern the future of man..."
- [I must not deceive you—you are to die], 1855-1860; uva.00280; xxx.00048; xxx.00015; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 4 x 14.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The verso lines (beginning "[I] and nobody else am the greatest traitor,") represent a later draft than similar verses in Library of Congress Notebook #80 of what would eventually become part of section 28 of Song of Myself. The recto lines were revised to form part of the 1860 poem To One Shortly To Die.
- [As procreation], about 1855; uva.00281; xxx.00431; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6 x 18.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The ideas expressed in this manuscript may have been used in the 1856 Poem of Remembrances for A Girl or A Boy of These States, which became the sixth poem in Chants Democratic and Native American in 1860. It was subsequently shortened by several stanzas (1867) and retitled (1872) Think of the Soul before being excluded from Leaves of Grass with the publication of the 1881 edition.
- [Of your soul I say truths to harmonize], about 1855; uva.00282; xxx.00716; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 7.5 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The verso contains the words "Leaves of" from a title page of one of the editions. The damaging of the words "The gripe" in the last line by cutting and the appearance of the tops of other letters above the lower edge suggest that this was the upper section of a larger leaf.
- [Who wills with his own brain], about 1855; uva.00283; xxx.00717; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 5 x 16 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  Draft lines of an incomplete poem, of which other parts may have been lost or never written. These lines display some similarities to the eleventh untitled poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass, named Lesson Poem in 1856 and finally, beginning with 1871's Passage to India, Who Learns My Lesson Complete?
- [Have I], about 1856; uva.00284; xxx.00221; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 9 x 18 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The words "Have I" at the beginning are inscribed on a small scrap of the same paper, which Whitman pasted over some deleted words in the upper right corner that cannot be discerned through the paper. Inscribed and extensively revised in pencil, these verses were part of a larger set of lines before Whitman cut away the rest. Although the page number and many words on the left side of the proof have been cut away, the remaining words identify it as being from the Poem of Many in One ( 1856 ), which eventually became By Blue Ontario's Shore. These unused but also undeleted lines may have been intended for that poem or a number of other poems in Leaves of Grass.
- [The beef, wheat, and lumber of Chicago], about 1855; uva.00285; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 10.5 x 19.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  Although these poetic notes are difficult to date, they may represent an intermediate stage between the 1855 Preface to Leaves of Grass and the 1856 Poem of Many in One (eventually By Blue Ontario's Shore), which cast many sentences similar to these from the Preface in poetic form.
- [O I must not forget], 1857-1859; uva.00286; xxx.00111; xxx.00047; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 14 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  Whitman's use of the tax form and the strong similarity this fragment bears both to the 1856 Poem of the Road (later Song of the Open Road) and to the 1860 Proto-Leaf (eventually Starting from Paumanok) indicate that this may have been a revision of the former poem or, as seems more likely, an early draft of Proto-Leaf intended for the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass.
- [Man, before the rage of whose passions], about 1855; uva.00287; xxx.00718; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 8 x 19.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  These verses seem to have been part of a larger set. Although written in free verse, the rather conventional nature of this poem suggests an early date of inscription.
- Broadway, 1888; uva.00156; xxx.00345; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 22.5 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 13, Folder Broadway)
  This manuscript contains a draft version of the poem Broadway. A note appearing at the top of the page states "Sent Herald March 3—sent again April 9 '88" indicating that this manuscript was likely composed and/or edited around the time of its first publication in the New York Herald, April 10, 1888.
- [No birth-identity], around 1888; uva.00159; xxx.00349; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 25.5 cm x 19.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 21, Folder Continuities)
  This manuscript contains a draft of the poem first published in the New York Herald, March 20, 1888 with the title Continuities. A note at the bottom of the page states "Sent to H March 17" indicating the draft was likely completed near the time of publication.
- A Carol-Cluster at 69, 1887; uva.00157; xxx.00315; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 15, Folder A Carol-Cluster at 69)
  This manuscript contains a draft version of a poem entitled A Carol-Cluster at 69 which was likely composed and edited around the time of its first publication in the New York Herald, May 21, 1888. In the same year, this poem appears in the annex Sands at Seventy under the title A Carol Closing Sixty-nine.
- Carols at nearing Seventy, around 1887; uva.00158; xxx.00315; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 28 cm x 21.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 16, Folder Carols Closing Sixty-Nine)
  This manuscript contains a draft version of a poem appearing with two alternative titles: Carols at Nearing Seventy and Carols Closing Sixty-Nine. A note at bottom states "Sent to Lippincotts." The poem was first published with the title in the New York Herald, May 21, 1888. In the same year, this poem appears in the annex Sands at Seventy under the title A Carol Closing Sixty-nine.
- The Dead Emperor, 1888; uva.00160; xxx.00370; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 11 cm x 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 27, Folder The Dead Emperor)
  This manuscript contains a draft of a poem first published in the New York Herald, March 10, 1888 entitled The Dead Emperor. A note at top of the page states "sent Herald March 8" indicating that the draft was likely composed around the time of publication. On the verso appears part of a letter with Houghton Mifflin Publishers letterhead.
- [Simple and Fresh], around 1888; uva.00162; xxx.00322; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 26 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 35, Folder The First Dandelion)
  This manuscript contains a draft of a poem first published in the New York Herald, March 12, 1888 entitled The First Dandelion. A note on the bottom of the page states "sent to Herald March 11" indicating the draft was likely composed around the time of publication. On the verso appears a letter to Whitman from Witcraft dated 3/8/88.
- Old Age's Lambent Peaks, 1880s; uva.00164; xxx.00375; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 25 cm x 20.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 66, Folder Old Age's Lambent Peaks)
  This manuscript contains a draft of a poem first printed in the Century, September, 1888 entitled Old Age's Lambent Peaks. A note in the top margin states: "sent to Century accepted—paid" indicating the draft was likely completed around the time of publication. Thee poem was collected into reprints of Leaves of Grass in the Annex of the 1884-88 editions and in the Birthday edition of 1889.
- [To-day], 1887; uva.00169; xxx.00325; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 71, Folder Orange Buds by Mail from Florida 3 copies)
  Manuscript draft of a poem first appearing in print in the New York Herald, April 23, 1888 entitled To-day and Thee. A note in the top margin: "sent April 21 to Herald" indicates that the draft was likely completed around the time of publication.
- Orange buds by mail, 1887; uva.00165; xxx.00366; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 14.5 cm x 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 71, Folder Orange Buds by Mail from Florida 3 copies, Page 1)
  A manuscript draft of the poem eventually titled Orange Buds by Mail from Florida and first published in the New York Herald, March 19, 1888.
- Orange Buds by Mail from Florida, 1887; uva.00001; xxx.00366; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 15.5 cm x 32.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 71, Folder Orange Buds by Mail from Florida 3 copies, Page 2)
  This manuscript contains a draft version of the note that appears in brackets before the start of the poem titled Orange Buds by Mail from Florida and first published in the New York Herald, March 19, 1888. A note at the bottom of the page states: "Sent to H March 17" indicating the draft was likely completed around the time of publication. On the verso the words "Walt Whitman" and "Camden New Jersey" are written in an unknown hand.
- Paumanok, 1888; uva.00166; xxx.00312; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 14 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 75, Folder Paumanok)
  This manuscript contains a draft of the poem titled Paumanok first published in the New York Herald, February 29, 1888. Notes at the top state "pub'd" and "personal." A note at the bottom states "sent to Herald Feb 27 '88" indicating the draft was likely completed around the time of publication.
- A Prairie Sunset, around 1888; uva.00167; xxx.00364; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 14 cm x 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 79, Folder A Prairie Sunset)
  This manuscript contains a draft of the poem titled A Prairie Sunset first published in the New York Herald, March 9, 1888. A note at the top states: "sent to Herald March 2" indicating the draft was likely completed around the time of publication.
- [With every heaving wave], 1880s; uva.00168; xxx.00310; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 24 cm x 14.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 25, Folder Sands at Seventy)
  This manuscript contains a draft version of the poem By That Long Scan of Waves included in the group of poems Fancies at Navesink. The group was first published in Nineteenth Century, August, 1885.
- The Wallabout Martyrs, 1888; uva.00171; xxx.00321; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 11.5 cm x 20.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 17, Folder The Wallabout Martyrs)
  This manuscript contains a draft version of the poem The Wallabout Martyrs first published in the New York Herald, March 16, 1888. A note at the bottom states: "sent to Herald March 11" indicating the draft was likely completed around the time of publication. On the verso of the leaves appear scraps of a letter and an envelope addressed to Whitman in Camden.
- You tides with ceaseless swell, 1888-1889; uva.00140; xxx.00333; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 25 cm x 19.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 26)
  One leaf in ink on lined paper with pencil revisions. This poem You Tides with Ceaseless Swell was first published as part of the Fancies at Navesink group in Nineteenth Century, August 1885.
- Sea-Drift, uva.00135; xxx.00130; poetry corrected proofs 20 leaves 20 cm x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 86)
  Revision of poem cluster originally titled Sea-Shore Memories contained in red bound volume measuring 26 cm x 18 cm. Revisions are made in ink and pencil on printed edition of the poem. WW apparently used two volumes to tear the leaves from, as every other page is slightly smaller than the rest; revisions are made only on the recto side of each leaf, verso is crossed out. Several leaves are cut apart and pasted in new order on other leaves or on lined paper. Leaf 8 is a handwritten MS.
- Song of the Broad-Axe, uva.00141; xxx.00116; poetry corrected proofs 23 leaves 20 cm x 12 cm 20 leaves 20 cm x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 89)
  Revision of poem cluster Song of the Broad-Axe contained in red slipcase measuring 24 cm x 15 cm. Revisions are made in ink and blue pencil on printed edition of the poem. WW apparently used two volumes to tear the leaves from, as every other page is slightly smaller than the rest, revisions are made only on the recto side of each leaf, and verso is crossed out.
- To an Exclusive, uva.00139; xxx.00719; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 20.5 cm x 13 cm (Box 2, Folder 11)
  This manuscript contains lines of an unpublished poem comparing the power of the voice of the poet and the common man to the "Exclusive." Whitman challenges future generations to follow his lead in representing those who remain unheard and to "respond to whatever needs response" at that time. The verso of the second leaf is an ordered list of poems beginning with "33 A Handful of Air" and ending with "72 Leaf."
- Poem of Names, 1850-1860; uva.00294; xxx.00720; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 7.5 cm x 12.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Pencil on white paper. Pasted on top half of archival leaf.
- [?Poem of different incidents], 1850-1860; uva.00295; xxx.00721; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 7.5 cm x 12.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Notes toward a "poem of different incidents" are written in ink on pink paper, pasted on the bottom half of the leaf.
- Mothers precede all, 1850-1860; uva.00296; xxx.00722; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 8 cm x 13.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Pencil on verso of envelope. Pasted on top half of archival leaf.
- [In Poems], 1850-1860; uva.00297; xxx.00001; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 7.5 cm x 15.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Ink on blue paper. Pasted on bottom half of archival leaf. Verso has some notes for poem [America, so young and so magnificent].
- [Intersperse here and], 1850-1860; uva.00300; xxx.00723; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 5.5 cm x 8 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Written in ink. Pasted on top third of archival leaf.
- Poem of Kisses, 1850-1860; uva.00301; xxx.00724; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 5 cm x 9.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Written in ink. Pasted in middle of archival leaf.
- Song in Poem of Kisses, 1850-1860; uva.00302; xxx.00725; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 7.5 cm x 11.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Written in pencil. Pasted on bottom third of archival leaf.
- Poem illustrative of the Woman under the 'new dispensation', 1850-1860; uva.00303; xxx.00726; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 17 cm x 16 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Written in ink. Pasted to own archival leaf.
- [You woman, mother of children], 1850-1860; uva.00137; xxx.00048; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 24.5 cm x 24.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 2)
  This manuscript contains images of women as mother and wife. The husband and wife together at night appears consistently as one of the images used in the poem ultimately titled Song of Myself throughout all of the editions of Leaves of Grass.
- As I Sit in Twilight, Late, or twilight song, around 1865 or 1888; uva.00147; xxx.00398; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 30 cm x 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Manuscript draft of the poem As I Sit in Twilight which Whitman eventually retitled A Twilight Song and published in Century, May 1890.
- [As I sit in twilight alone by the flicker], around 1865 or 1888; uva.00002; xxx.00398; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 26 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
- As I sit in twilight, around 1865 or 1888; uva.00003; xxx.00398; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 27 cm x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Unknown, around 1865 or 1888; uva.00004; xxx.00398; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 28.5 cm x 19.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Manuscript draft of a poem Whitman titled Unknown and which eventually became A Twilight Song which was published in Century, May 1890.
- Unknown, around 1865 or 1888; uva.00005; xxx.00398; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 27.5 cm x 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
- As of Forms, around 1860; uva.00124; xxx.00611; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21.5 cm x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Manuscript draft of the unpublished poem As of Forms which is possibly one of a group of poems Whitman composed prior to the third edition of Leaves of Grass.
- Old Age Echoes, 1891; uva.00152; xxx.00397; xxx.00407; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 52.5 cm x 21.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 65)
  The general title, Old Age Echoes, appears at the top of the page. Beneath that title are two poems with individual titles: Sounds of the Winter and The Unexpress'd. Pasted to the leaf below the second poem is a woodcut engraving of Whitman along with his autograph. The untitled lines directly following the picture and autograph eventually become the poem titled After the Argument. The three poems were first published together in Lippincott's Magazine, March 1891, under the general title Old Age Echoes.
- A Glint inside of Abraham Lincoln's Appointment - one item of many [A Glint inside of Abraham Lincoln], 22 August 1865; uva.00406; xxx.00481; #9778 item 5; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 39)
  This manuscript contains a large part of the account of Abraham Lincoln's appointment of James Harlan as Secretary of the Interior, which was first published in November Boughs in 1888 with the title of Small Memoranda and was later retained the Complete Prose Works, published in 1892.
- Elias Hicks [Elias Hicks], 1888; uva.00055; xxx.00486; #3829; prose 5 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 30)
  This manuscript contains a biographical note about the religious leader and abolitionist Elias Hicks (1748-1830). Parts of this note would be published in Notes (Such as They Are) Founded on Elias Hicks in November Boughs in 1888 and was later retained in the Complete Prose Works, published in 1892.
- The Dead Emerson [The Dead Emerson], 1882; uva.00057; xxx.00904; #3829; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder 26)